be admitted.
Uh, admitting all
and good afternoon everybody. This is
Dominic with the New Mexico Department
of Health and we are here to help and
assist with regard to uh the uh today's
committee meeting which is the equity
and access committee with Desba as the
chair. And while people are uh joining
into the meeting, we'll give them just a
minute or two. And in the meantime, um
just as a reminder, we do have everybody
on mute and other than some department
staff and um and Desba as the chair, uh
we do not have the cameras turned on.
And the reason why we do that is one
because we do record these meetings and
put them up publicly. They have to get
reviewed and we want to make sure that
there are no inappropriate language or
images in the background. The other
reason for why we don't keep all of our
cameras on and in fact in a moment after
the introductions you'll see me turn my
camera off except when I'm speaking is
mostly because uh we understand that
there are areas of the state where
bandwidth when they're when people are
connecting to the internet is not as
good as we would like and so in order to
help people not drop off and have to
rejoin um at least any more than they
need to we try to reduce that bandwidth
and visual the visual side actually adds
to the bandwidth quite a bit. And so
with that in mind, um I will turn this
on over to Desba. And Deszba is the
meeting is all yours. I will go ahead uh
put the agenda into the chat. So
>> y hi, good afternoon. Um welcome back. I
know some of you might have been going
to some other meetings that we've had.
Um I can barely remember what day it is.
um or the time, but we are back from the
legislative session for those of you who
have um been keeping up with things. A
couple of announcements. I do have an
agenda that I'm trying to follow. Um
uh so we are still awaiting um MLG, our
governor, uh to sign the equity fund
money that uh Senator Jeff Steinborn was
able to secure was about $630,000
I believe. Um and she has until today uh
technically I guess 115959
to sign um off on that um the money. Um
so that is one of the things that we are
Oh she did she just signed. Awesome.
Thank you Denali for that update. Um
yay. So that is the money that we are
going to have to figure out how it is
going to be uh spent and or um
distributed through the patient model
for the medical psilocybin um trials
that we are approving and regulating
etc. um for the future that will be
starting I believe next year January 1
is that right? Um, and so that's one of
the things. Um,
and then also as well on the native
tribal side of things, um, we are still
looking at trying to gather all of the
governors who were just recently elected
in January. um and making it more of a
formal
gathering to get input and at least just
to start having that conversation. Um
for some people who may not be familiar
um nav uh the tribal governor governance
nations they are sovereign um it's
essentially like having our own country
within the state of New Mexico within
the United States of America. So they
have their own governance, how they deal
with things, how they do things even
within the borders of New Mexico and the
United States. Um so having that
relationship, having that right
relationship is really important. The
governors change every year. So that's
also another um added challenge or um
you know making sure that everything
between fed, government and communities
is um
taken care of. Um so those are just kind
of the really updates. Uh
and with that
we're going to and that to me that's
essentially the updates that we have.
One more thing that was not put on the
agenda which I just recently learned
which is not exactly
specific to the medical psilocybin but
just to put it on people's radar. Um
recently we uh Native Americans were
able to gain access for their healing
ceremonies through Medicaid uh thanks to
one of our cohorts in part to one of our
cohorts um uh Elena Elena Danis Dances.
Um
uh sorry my brain is not helping me
today but if you haven't seen the
article there is one in Santa Fe New
Mexican regarding that. Um, it's really
important. I think that's also perhaps
one of the points um of information that
we could be looking at um because access
and equity through Medicaid, what those
models look like, having that be um
something that we know that um
psilocybin, psychedelics
um in general are a part of traditional
healing pathways for native people um
and their pra and cultural practices.
So, who knows if there will be a
potential um New Mexico medical covers
traditional native healing ceremony. So,
I'm not quite exactly sure all about
that, but I think it's something that
would be really important for um our
committee to look into um if there is
already something in place and how
that's going to be accessible with the
um medical psilocybin if at all.
Um, so with that, we're going to go
ahead and go into our um
PowerPoint presentation
to review our purpose. Um, let's see.
It's going sign up for updates.
Okay. Oh, we don't have it in this in
this one, but can we can we pull that up
or somewhere? Sorry. I'm grabbing it.
I'm grabbing it right now so that we
>> Awesome. Okay. Yeah. Just to be able to
review the purpose and the
responsibilities of what this committee
is. Um so far in the past um
meetings. It's mostly just been trying
to understand um the
landscape of the different concerns. We
have been hearing people from Oregon. We
have been hearing people from Colorado.
We have been hearing from people in New
York. We do o uh we are open to
information and input from other people
in other states and how that can
potentially affect and or work with New
Mexico's citizens. New Mexico citizens
are the priority um for this particular
um board and the committees. Um, and so
we're looking at other ways in which
Oregon has seen challenges or other ways
in which Colorado has seen challenges or
information that is coming in from New
York. We have had lawyers um bringing in
information. We have propagation um
specialists um we have also had
facilitators out of state and also
within state talking about the things
that they see that are important as far
as um providing equity and access on
both sides. To me that is both the
facilitator propagation and patient
sides of things. How are we able to have
access for for everyone?
Um
okay. And do we have the purpose and I'm
sorry the Oh, there it is. Okay. Got it.
>> Uh yeah, I'm trying to bring it on up.
It's just uh I just had the PowerPoint
up and then it uh dropped off on me.
>> So give me just a moment. I'm getting it
back up there.
>> Okay. So while you're doing that, I will
go ahead and read them. Purpose and
responsibilities. Purpose is to ensure
that New Mexico's medical psilocybin
services system is accessible,
culturally appropriate, responsive to
the needs of indigenous
rural frontier.
Indigenous rural frontier. Is there is
should there be another comma in there?
Indigenous comma rural or is it
indigenous rural? uh frontier, Hispanic,
and underserved communities and the
program implementation that promotes
equity, inclusion,
um and culturally grounded care across
all settings. So, that's a mouthful for
sure. Um and the responsibilities are
recommend to the board policies to
expand access to rural frontier and
underserved areas in New Mexico
including but not limited to tea health
enabled screening and rural training.
Tellaalth was something that was brought
up initially um in one of the first
meetings. um that is a model that can be
used with as a recommendation to the
board and um what that looks like. Also
recommend anti-discrimination and
anti-stigma policies within the
psilocybin services system. Uh recommend
policies that ensure culturally
appropriate practices for indigenous and
Hispanic communities. recommend
qualifications and process for
determination for eligibility of
financial assistance through the patient
equity fund. Um so number four as we
said is the first step of that is MLG
signing that and she did today. um and
learning how
we the board or the recommendations to
the administration of the department of
health um can provide assistance to
these people um to the people that need
it the most which is making sure that we
have um equity amongst New Mexicans.
Uh and then also too even though it will
it's it's within the language of of this
um
paper this pres presentation that's from
front of you um is how that the equity
access is intersecting with all the
other committees for instance
propagation that we are able to have
access for everyone whether it's um fin
at the financial cost level. We have
testing that's involved. Are we allow
are we allowing our New Mexican growers
to be able to have access within reason
to paying for being able to um provide
their medicine for uh New Mexican
citizens as well as is it is the
training that we are allowing permitting
and regulating um licensing etc. Uh, is
that also cost prohibitive? Or is it
being able to
uh be able to be able to afford to to
train and to renew licenses or permits
and or how does that look? Um, what
kinds of training are we looking at?
And, you know, is it
thousands of dollars? Yes, you're
investing in yourself and you're
investing in in the future of care of
people, but you know, it it could
potentially be cost prohibitive to some
people and we are trying to make sure to
find that com um the intersection of
that.
Um let's see. Okay. So to move on from
looking at the purpose and the
responsibilities,
it is important that we figure out how
and for whom that we're going to create
the policies to expand access to rural
frontier underserved areas in New
Mexico, including but not limited to
teleaalth and enabled screening and
rural training. Um
this is where it gets a little bit
nuanced I guess. Um the only other for
those who may not be familiar with what
this is asking and this is my
understanding is in uh comparison to say
the film industry and I've used this
example before um what does rural look
like is you know what is the epicenter
the central point and the what that
radius is expanding from
for instance in the film industry when
it comes to figuring out where rural is,
whether it's in Santa Fe or in
Albuquerque, that mile radius will
either include or exclude certain
certain cities or towns. In the case of
Los Cusus,
it's considered rural, but
that
is to a lot of people misleading
because it's a big town, right? So these
are the things that's the example I'm
going to give. Those are the things that
we have to kind of look at. What does it
mean to be rural and where are we
looking at this um radius to include or
exclude some people? Um are we looking
at big towns? What does that look like?
Um so I've also used the example of
different communities culturally.
Farmington area which is a border town,
Gallup also which is a border town. um
they are bordering Navajo Nation, their
needs and what their uh care plan or how
they're going to be um providing access
for their community might look different
than what say is happening in Los Cusus,
Roswell, Los Alamos, Santa Fe,
Espanella, Raton, Clayton or Portales.
And what we're supposed to be doing as
far as the equity and access and
cultural considerations is trying to
find somewhere that is not necessarily
cookie cutter but standard baseline. Um
so that we can make sure that we are
covering as many people as possible. not
excluding people but also um
understanding for instance in the case
of tribal governance that they have
sovereignty that they are able to choose
for themselves in their community. Um
what I am thinking is a lot of it is
education but the even education is
broad term. What does that actually
really look like? What are these
definitions? How is this going to
actually be implemented? And that's
where we need um people who are on the
ground actually in these communities
talking about things that they are
seeing that they need. I know that we
had one lawyer from Mura or that was
representing
um in Las Vegas and Mura um the
teleaalth idea when it comes especially
to psilocybin
um and its use there are different
stages where we are evaluating the a
patient's needs and what are what would
those um
assessing the patient's needs but what
do those uh patient.
God, someone help me here with uh
presenting.
I promise this is like this is the thing
that I've been dealing with like for the
last few months. Um
diagnosis, their diagnosis. um what do
they look like and who is going to be um
service with with whatever diagnosis
they might have whether it's PTSD
is are we including domestic violence
cases are we including um other me
mental health issues are we excluding
some where
if diagnosed by a doctor
that they feel um
that medical psilocybin may not be
advised
for use. um in the case of and I'm you
know just throwing something out here uh
schizophrenia for instance maybe that
might be something that is not advised
but in the case of a PTSD or complex uh
PTSD diagnosis as such we are also if
anyone is interested in those types of
things there are also committees for um
patient care um and in creating finding
out what those
presenting symptoms are um and where
medical assignment would be um advised.
Um but what those look like and
we need to imple finding where those are
being implemented in addition to
uh the communities that might need it
the most and what does that look like?
Um,
and in this example, I'm going to say I
think Rioba, TA County, and I think
Santa Fe County most recently, as of I
think the beginning of 2025, they had
higher incidences of uh, fentinel
overdoses.
Those three counties specifically, for
instance, they may have the data that
presents um,
that that would be where the equity fund
might provide more of the money. I'm not
saying that this is the case that this
is an example. Um but then what does
that look like say for in instances of
Roswell County or especially like I said
border towns such as Farmington and
Gallup. Um so people who are on the
ground we do necess we do definitely
need your um
insight input um where where these
instances um we're going to need the
most um screenings um for
the demonstrated need to implement the
equity fund and what that looks like.
Um, so it's defining things for whom
that's that's what it is when we're
saying like for whom is the money going
to be spent,
which particular areas may seem like
they are the most in need andor are we
going to say for instance allowing
specific places to of their own agency
decide whom of their patients might need
um
a funding financial funding for for them
specifically.
So is it like a clinic that's in uh some
of the clinics that are in Rioba County
are are they some of the clinics that
are in Ta County and also here in Santa
Fe County? We also don't want to again
like I said leave out any of the more
rural populations
um what that looks like. So,
now that I'm done talking, I haven't
seen if there's anything in the chat. Is
there anything in the chat that I need
to look at?
>> No, Despa, not at this point. But what I
would recommend is that uh we see if
people have ideas with regard to the um
for the first portion with regard to
like teleaalth and how to reach rural
areas.
>> Yeah. So is anybody how anyone in the
chat?
>> Okay, Dr. Linda Fatim, I am
allowing your mic.
Sorry, I'm having a little issue with
it.
We're trying to allow your mic. I
apologize.
Okay, it is um open. You may unmute
yourself, Dr. Linda Fetamy.
>> Thank you so much. And and it's Lita
Vami. Um I know it's an unusual name and
I have my son in the background. You're
going to hear as well. Um but I want to
thank you so much for the considerations
you've brought up Desba and the
committee. Um
>> yes.
And um
regarding teleaalth, I see that being
utilized especially when we're uh in
training training individual training
medical providers in the rural areas.
You know, right now we have um an
addiction specialist uh NP down in
Silver City who's training with us and I
see her being that spot point of
community healing for her community of
patients.
Um for tella health I can see micro
doing able for us to be able to utilize
micro doing
um macro dosing I don't advise it to be
utilized through tele health and I'm
going to stop there because my little
one is not letting me continue sorry
>> thank you for um your input and um I
think there is if Dominic I don't know
if you wanted to go ahead and bring it
up. It's a little ways far back in did
provide um a possible proposal um back
in the draft section of the comm of the
uh dashboard. Um
and as far as what we were thinking with
the telea medicine for preparation
sessions and yes no go ahead desp you
you just started launching into it so go
ahead.
>> Okay. Yeah. Um, this is just a proposal.
I'll go ahead and read through it. Um,
it says, you know, New Mexico continues
to experience a critical shortage of
licensed medical and behavioral health
providers, particularly in rural
frontier communities. Residents of rural
New Mexico face persistent barriers to
timely affordable geographically
accessible health care services. Tellah
health telea medicine has demonstrated
to expand access to medical and
behavioral health care improve community
of care continuity of care and mitigate
provider short shortages in underserved
areas equitable access to emerging and
regulated
>> that's what I was doing I was it just I
wasn't expecting us to go
>> uh equitable access to emerging and
regulated therapies including psilocybin
services requires flexible delivery
models that accommodate geographic and
workforce limitations. Um this is more
of a a whereas proposal um
that the proposal is that for the equity
purposes the committee recommends the
dosage administration and clinicals
practice committee that telea medicine
services defined below are for
preparation sessions. Um to kind of put
people back up to speed a little bit. It
was I think believe uh in the first
committee meeting that this was brought
up about utilizing tellaalth. Um I think
tellaalth was something that was already
provided through Medicaid. Um Dominic
can correct me if I got that wrong. Um
and in through utilizing teleaalth
within the Medicaid insurance system, I
don't know if it's through all
insuranceances.
um that at least
the preparation sessions could be um
provided with a facilitator. Um it was
strongly suggested that it would be for
the preparation sessions only as we are
dealing with a medicine
um that has the component. We don't know
how much of a dosage even in micro doing
to some people may be something that
needs a one-on-one in-person
um
facilitation. So the facilitation part
of it is where we kind of thought about
drawing a line with the teleaalth at
this point. Um so I'll read the tele
medicine service requirements. Um the
service must meet the following
requirements include audio and visual be
delivered on a real-time basis at the
originating and distant site no
restrictions on services that can be
offered via teleaalth
um and by that I believe it means um as
far as the assessment you know no
restrictions on the tellaalth you know
it could be anything um that's presented
if the provider resides It's outside of
New Mexico. Um
um this part I'm not sure this one seems
to be worded a little bit weirdly.
Uh meet the following require if
provider resides out of New Mexico is
licensed to provide Zilla services in
their respective state. Okay, got it.
Okay, so this is um for the facilitator.
If the provider resides outside of New
Mexico, say they're in Colorado or
Oregon, um they have their licensing
there, um that they're licensed to
provide psilocybin services within their
respective state and completed New
Mexico specific training program.
This one I will kind of highlight to
bring attention to. I'm not sure quite
exactly.
Um, I feel like that one might need to
be
uh evaluated and looked into um for my
personal
thought. If there's anyone who is in the
meeting would like to pipe up about any
of the things that were read or any
other further thoughts or conversation
on this particular proposal to
the board
in agreement with this or not
>> we do have a couple of hands up. The
first one is Denali.
>> Okay
Denali you can unmute yourself.
Hi. Um,
this is helpful. It was uh a little hard
to follow just because we can't see the
proposal, but maybe it can be shared
some other uh another way. I'll just
mention I think I understand the policy
restriction
um for
um non-administration
days. Um, but I I I do think it would um
make sense to also include authorization
for integration in in addition to
preparation. So, if we're if we're
wanting to restrict the in-person days
to administration for therapeutic doses,
uh I don't think we need to exclude
integration. um but would would like to
hear other other thoughts especially
from the providers who are on the line
about whether there is a need to have
that happen in person.
>> So Denali just to let you know I did put
it in the chat um so that you can
actually read it there in the chat. No
that's okay. Um but the other thing too
is this was just an initial item from
Ian. he wasn't meaning it to necessarily
um restrict in other aspects of the
therapeutic side just the administration
aspect like Desba was talking about. So
this is just an example for uh how it
might be with regard to preparation
sessions but it's really good to hear
the feedback of it being included for
those other therapeutic aspects as well.
So definitely thank you on that.
>> Dr. Amy, you may unmute yourself.
>> Thank you. Um I agree with Denali and
and uh Dominic. Yes, integration can
absolutely be done through teleaalth as
well. Um I you know in general like the
proposal that you read Desba one um
comment is about facilitators in other
states uh serving our individuals in our
state. Um though I you know I'm I'm for
it if we are we don't have enough
facilitators in our state. I would say
that that should be a secondary thing
where the facilitators in our state
where also the um contributions back
into our land and into our community and
people uh would be important
economically for facilitators who are on
the ground. know this population, know
our community, know our indigenous and
cultural needs to be the, you know,
facilitators that maybe get the first
go.
Um, and and then we look at if if we are
lacking, you know, facilitators here to
then go out of state. That's the only
other comment I had. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Um and then to both of those two
point um you know that this was
definitely for the preparation sessions
like the initial um evaluation sessions
but it is very good to put a note that
tellaalth would be also potentially
advisable and or not um would be
beneficial for the integration sessions.
So those it's still valuable feedback
both from Denali and Dr. uh Fatmi um
Fatim uh for that. Um and I and I and I
do feel like that is another highlight
for this potential
uh proposal is just the idea of outside
and this was like back like three months
ago that I got this uh particular piece
of information. Um I just wanted to make
sure that we are looking at things like
this and this is good. We don't have to
play nice sometimes with our opinions
about, you know, you know, it needs to
be for New Mexicans, by New Mexicans.
Totally. You know, that's a great
recommendation. Um, to be to have a
strong recommendation that it's by New
Mexicans, for New Mexicans, totally on
board with anybody who has a a stronger
opinion. um but also willing to listen
to this idea that we are gonna be um h
have a little bit more open borders and
I and who who knows it may not even be
able to work out that way um as far as
uh who we are allowing to be able to
provide for for New Mexicans but I think
to Dr. uh Fatami's point, you know, if
initially or at some point where there
are none there's just like this influx,
maybe that might be a good um what do
you call circling back to um in the case
of like what would we do if everybody is
so booked up that they have no more no
more appointments available and someone
really needs to have that care and
especially for instance, let's just say
um I'm not sure exactly why that was put
in there, but I'm just thinking like uh
Farmington, Kirtland, any of those
places where you are right across the
border. Maybe there is somebody that you
have a good relationship with. And it
might be that case where you have a
relationship with someone who is not
necessarily in New Mexico and maybe that
would, you know, why can't why can't
they choose someone that they trust? I
can I can imagine. Um I think that there
is a question in the chat.
Um if we could go ahead and address
that. Does anyone already read through
it before I I mean I can read through it
but
>> yeah uh does Bob we haven't actually
read it but I was actually working on a
response in the chat so um I'll go ahead
and this is the one from uh Kenny I'm
sorry
>> Kina Kina I apologize if I am
>> uh completely mispronouncing your name
um my apologies but um it was about the
question that came up during research
and continuous this improvement and just
really talking about race being an issue
and about whether or not an individual
had previously used psychedelics and um
what the clinician benefits are with
regard to having that information during
the screening process. Um, and then that
the question that it brings potentially
uh significant stronger emotional
responses for people of color who are
under greater scrutiny and at higher
risk for prosecution and discussing
about while it's a legal medical
program. The concern is that a question
about prior use may be alienating for
those in BIPO communities for folks of
color on this committee. Is it a
question prior use perhaps legal but
quite possibly underground and one that
could have the potential to prevent
those individuals to utilize care? And
one thing to remember is there is also
going to be a big difference in many
ways between the um the research aspects
where people are choosing to be in those
research areas and the medical aspect of
the program. So someone going in for
treatment and for example someone going
in simply for the treatment aspects the
program for example is not going to be
gathering or containing all of that
information as far as prior use. We're
going to really be looking at has the
clinician done their due diligence with
the the patient and do they recommend
and attest that that this patient would
actually benefit from treatment. And so
that's a great question and it's one
that we've been talking about quite a
bit as far as what could potentially be
problematic as far as questions to be
asked. Um, and I think some of it is
there's that balance between um, you
know, people wanting to gather as much
information as possible because these
are new programs and we need that
research side as well as balancing it
with the needs of the patient and those
potential issues with regard to legal
legality, prosecution, those sort of
things. don't have exact answers yet as
what that that balance will be, but
that's a part of this concern and a part
of this process is going through it. Um,
I do see that Denali does have her hand
up again. Uh, Denali,
>> hi. Hi again. Um, I just wanted to offer
uh two I, you know, making sure that the
therapy parts are included in teleaalth
feels important. I'm trying to remember
back to I think it was Brett's um
initial contributions around tellaalth.
Um but I I do think there was a
conversation then around whether and and
I heard it in Dr. Fatmy's um initial
comment around the potential of micro
doing right not not every dose is a
behavioral health heroic dose right and
especially if even if we're not talking
about micro doing but pain protocols
that are much lower doses it's not a
qualifying condition now but we want to
make regulations that um that are
evergreen right um that we that are as
expansive as they can be. I I'm
wondering whether maybe it makes sense
for um rather than a full preclusion of
administration and tellaalth um certain
safety requirements including a dosage
um a dosage threshold. I know
logistically it will be um there there
are a number of different challenges to
to move through but if we're talking
about small doses one of the things that
has diverted a lot of micro doses and
lower doses and especially pain patients
from the regulated market to um or the
the regulated um space in Oregon and
Colorado is isn't in in accessibility
because of the inperson requirements
that really from a safety perspective um
don't aren't as necessary um though they
are tremendously necessary from a
behavioral if we're talking about a
therapeutic dose um it just really the
the care is different so um I I know
we're just having a an exploratory
conversation now but I I didn't want to
endorse the full exclusion of
administration but thinking about
creative ways we might be able to infuse
safety if that is a dosage threshold and
other parameters, you know, making sure
that there is someone else with someone
that can be vetted, right? Um, this gets
connected to to homebound use and and
those kinds of things. So, as long as
we're keeping the conversation open, um,
I'm grateful to to know that we're
prioritizing teleaalth and
accessibility.
>> Okay. So from what I'm hearing from what
you're saying Denali essentially is you
know maybe having just putting a pin in
this idea of what does the dosage look
like when it comes to the teleaalth
assessment portion. Um
and I think that we could probably break
up the teleaalth portion into say three
different uh sessions right you have the
evaluation session you have a potential
for a journey let's just call it journey
session and then you have the teleaalth
for a integration session right and so
what I'm hearing from uh you is that
taking a look at the journey portion
based on an assessment of the need of
the person, whether or not the
facilitator may or may not advise a
micro dose. And that micro dose may or
may not be X.1
grams, etc., whatever is based on the
dosage um committee recommendations.
um that that would might be okay given
given that there are parameters and
andor something that's kind of what I'm
hearing from you is that during the
quote journey portion of a tea potential
tellaalth uh uh facilitation
um that the dosage committee might look
into
what does a micro dose look like for
teaalth during a journey session
in a rural environment with certain
parameters enabled with access to
doctors or you know like what are the
lifelines that are involved during that
journey process is what I'm hearing
Denali essentially
we have a thumbs up or
>> despa you you've got it and I I see Dr.
wants to chime in too. I just like if we
think about a migraine protocol for
example um right which is a like one
gram um every week for 3 weeks I could
imagine as we create a safety mechanism
where for the first one say someone
lives in a rural community we're
requiring somebody to come in for the
first session and have inerson
facilitation to see and monitor how they
do um but it will become really cost
prohibitive if we require that travel
especially for someone suffering from
chronic pain um and there may be right I
don't I'm not the clinician here and I
do want to hear from clinicians but in a
non right where I wouldn't call it the
journey day because the idea is that
there's no there's not really journeying
that's happening that's what allows for
the this the safety of a potential
remote supervision um but but if that's
possible we want to be sure I'm really
thinking about pain protocols and and
ways that that might be possible.
>> Okay. Yeah. And and I forgive me for not
using proper termin. We're still kind of
figuring out what the definitions are.
So my definition of the journey was just
like you're on you're you popped the
pill or whatever. You've taken the
mushroom, you're eating it, you're now
one with one with the mushroom. Um, and
just to kind of point out for anyone
else who's listening, do understand that
one gram of any specific cultivation or
cultivator, it can potentially be
totally different than a gram of a
different cultivator. And they we're
also keeping that in mind as if anyone
is involved in the propagation
committees. Um, they are looking at
opening it up to any number of
cultivators for the program. um as a
recommendation. These are all
recommendations. Nothing is put into
existence in writing yet. This is all
we're just thinking about. What does
this look like? Um so that is one of the
things to keep in mind. So one gram
could be completely fine on a specific
cultivator. One gram might be like
you're off into the clouds on a
different cultivator. So we also have to
kind of keep those things in mind when
we're talking about what does a micro
dose look like? Um okay. And then um so
those are good valid points and I and I
I hear that you're saying that's very
specific with the symptoms that are
presenting and the evaluations based on
the facilitator etc. Um Dr. Fati.
>> Yes, thank you so much. And yeah, I love
the points you're bringing up, um,
Denali Andes, but um, so the micro doses
that, you know, um, I've utilized in the
past, we're talking like 50 milligrams
in a coaching session on Zoom or on
FaceTime or um, in a space where the
patient has access to it or the client.
And so um in those therapeutic
sessions that is through teaalth what
I've seen is a greater availability of
the person to their subconscious so they
can explore their trauma in a in an
observer seat instead of being so
involved in that resistance of you know
and fear of examination. And so and
we're talking very small doses. Uh and
I'm not just talking about I'm talking
more in in the realm of the behavioral
health coaching and therapeutic session
with the individual on the teleaalth
um um you know container um with those
very small doses which they don't need
to go to a center for. And yeah, I do
agree with you Denali that that you know
one gram can be a lot for some people
and they yeah that should be with
someone and yeah it could be cost
prohibitive for the subsequent um but
yeah we have to you know these are
things that we it's great to be talking
about and coming up with
recommendations.
Um, but I've seen incredible
work done with
um with a the in within a therapeutic
session, whether that's again a coaching
session, whether that's a therapy
session where you also have CBT type
thing that is integrated and a very
small amount again 50 milligrams or
maybe 100 milligrams of psilocybin then
is also taken together no more than that
and that is we know across through and
through that is the subperceptive dose
and I have not heard of you know I mean
I've done this for you know many years
now and have not seen anyone even with
extreme trauma or you know very little
trauma to have any adverse reaction to
50 milligrams and so um this that's
minuscule you know and in fact when I
give talks at psychedelic conferences
about this and the results that we're
seeing um for clients the people in the
psychedelic community are like what
you're using that little of a dose and
seeing this kind of a result reminding
us that it is that deep connection of
care and compassion of the facilitator
um and I'm not meaning in a macro do
session but that catalyst the individual
who's sitting for the person across that
telea visit or in person with that tiny
dose and also how much we care about
that person. We know psychologically
that makes a huge difference. And
secondly,
um, showing people
and giving them tools, our patients and
clients in the community,
how they can make themselves feel better
as well. Um, with breath work, with
meditation, and many other tools that
there are. And that's a very empowering
thing when combined with a very very low
dose of psilocybin.
Yeah. So, thank thank you. Yeah. No,
thank you for your insight into this.
What I'm hearing from both Denali and
Dr. Feti is a recommendation to talk
about it with the board um with the
dosage committee is um input is
providing
a teleaalth with consideration for
whatever they consider a micro dose is
essentially what I'm hearing as far as
you know don't overlook it, don't leave
it out. Tele tele medicine may or may
not be potentially advised with whatever
the dosage uh committee sees is a micro
dose and or less. That's that's what I'm
hearing because there are benefits
perhaps to the access um for people in
rural areas and or it may be financially
uh restrictive or the inperson portion
of it may or may not be restrictive.
That's what I'm hearing. Um, if there's
anybody else that has something to say
in the comments or to raise their hand
if they agree to that assessment of what
I'm hearing, we have like about 10 15ish
minutes left in our meeting here and I
just wanted to not leave anybody else
out. Okay, so that's the thumbs up from
Dr. Fatmi. Okay. Yeah, I think that
we're kind of this this might be a
little bit slow moving, but um that is
going to be a note in the tele medicine
um for for lack of a better way of
explaining it is the journey portion um
of after the assessment
and mainly for pain
for things. example for for for uh s
symptoms
such as
pain
that does migraines.
Okay, just so make sure I have a note in
there. Um
just going to
let's see
I feel like we have kind of looked at
this idea of tellahalth. There's
probably way more um to talk about with
that but I'm going to go back to the
agenda really quickly.
Um let's see. We also have enabled
screening and rural training to look at.
um
enabled screening and rural training.
>> All right.
>> So despa
health enabled screening. So that for
example the the clinician who is helping
to do some evaluations on for example
treatment resistant depression might be
able to do some aspects through
teleaalth. But I if I may um just
because we don't have a lot of time, it
would be really great to hear on the
from everybody because we're going to
start writing out some of the ideas
behind uh what needs to happen with
regard to the patient equity fund. And
since we only have a few minutes left,
if maybe we could spend a few minutes
just hearing from people that other than
financial assistance because we
recognize looking at things from whether
it's uh ends up being 200, 300 or
whatever it might be as far as percent
of uh income based on the federal
poverty level that we recognize that
there's going to be assistance from that
side. But what what other areas are
people going to need assistance? um that
could be provided through the equity
fund to help them and facilitate the
treatment. Now, I know we've talked also
about transportation for individuals who
are in rural frontier areas um to be
able to get to appointments, things like
that, but what other areas are there
that we need to look at to ensure that
access for the equity fund?
>> Yes, besides financial and
transportation, are there other aspects
Yeah. What do interpreters? Thank you,
Katherine. That's a very good one. So,
interpreters,
>> child and elder care. So, if someone's
going through their treatment, there's
also child care or elder care.
Okay?
And people can raise their hands too if
they have other ideas. But these are
great because this is exactly the kind
of thing we're trying to figure out. And
it's always great to have a group of
minds rather than just one or two.
>> Yeah. And I definitely as a as a as a
mom, the child care aspect is definitely
um a a huge one. Um, and especially when
you're looking at uh people in my age
bracket, we're not only taking care of
the little ones, we're also taking care
of the older ones as well. Um, and so we
need to make sure that we are providing
the support that people need both um
during
you know the sessions that are that are
are required. I mean these sessions
attorney journey sessions specifically
for instance could last several hours
and you know you may not be able to find
the time while the child is in school or
you know your someone is taking care of
like your elder. So Dr. the tummy.
>> Thank you. And I might have missed this
part, Dominic. You might have said it
already. Sorry about that if you I'm
repeating. But the question that I have
is um are we also talking about the
therapeutic sessions themselves? Are we
talking about the preparatory sessions?
because sometimes that takes a month or
two of sessions and also the integration
sessions afterwards uh takes a month or
two depending on the severity of the
trauma in the past and so forth. Is that
is that a part of the discussion here
for the
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's anything anything that having
some of that financial assistance could
help someone like like if it would be a
difference between an individual
receiving treatment and therapy or not
receiving it and it covers the entire
span. It's not just the day of
administration. It can include some of
those others. So yeah.
>> Yeah. Gotcha. Yeah. And often times
that's where we see that's being so
expensive too. It's, you know, if you
look at like therapists depending on
their experience, years of experience,
it's $150 to $300 an hour to sit with a
therapist. And um and if you need four
sessions or eight sessions of
preparation work beforehand or four
sessions and or eight sessions after the
uh you know the macro dose that this is
what we're talking about macro do
specifically then that I can see be very
cost prohibitive and individuals will
absolutely need financial um assistance
there.
>> Yeah. And then kind of I'm I'm going
just based off of the comment that's in
the chat. You know, the things to kind
of also look at is I mean 6 to I I'm not
sure exactly how the government looks at
$630, but given how things are costing a
lot of money nowadays, it doesn't it's
it's a great amount of money, but it's
also like it's it's limited at this
point, right? So we also have to kind of
look at um
we we don't want to have to look at but
how have to look at you know how many
sessions there are is this going to be
you know for all covering all three
sessions that sort of thing I don't know
Dominic you know th to me those are the
kinds of things that we also are looking
at because one person may need you know
it's like a one and I I want to say a
oneandone right it may be a one and
done. It could be that this is an
ongoing thing. Generally speaking, I
think a lot of people are essentially
one and done. um you know they they have
immense bene uh benefits after like one
really big session but we also need to
have the possibility of what does it
look like for for future sessions if
this is something that is going to be um
drawn out um for you know between
divvied up between several different
lower doses for instance I have no idea
what that looks like you know and or
what that might be advised um between
the facilitator and the patient Um, but
I think even nuance things like that, is
that correct, Dominic? We're like
looking at what does it look like not
just across the board, you know, are we
are we cutting some of these things in
half? Are we paying for half of the
dose? Are we paying for half of the
session? Are we paying for all of it?
>> So, again, some of that's going to
depend on financial abilities of the
individuals because again, this is about
equity and access. So it doesn't
necessarily mean that the equity fund
would pay for everyone. If we did that,
quite frankly, we might be able to
actually help fund maybe only a couple
hundred individuals. And so, especially
as there's some great comments in the
chat and we're making note of them. So,
if we're not responding right away to
them, please understand we are taking
notes on them. Um but the idea is is
that we um you know that we be able to
actually spread this out among as many
different people as possible to ensure
that there's equity on it. And so some
of it's going to depend on what the
patient themselves might be able to pay.
For example, you know, we want to make
sure that individuals who have lower
income are able to access this treatment
just like people who otherwise and we've
heard this a lot that you know people
who can access this therapy in Oregon
and Colorado have money. So we want to
ensure individuals who do not have money
are also able to access this based upon
the need. But we are going to have to
figure out what kind of um uh areas
there are. So it may be sliding scale
depending on various factors like maybe
on transport there's only so much that
we can help cover and maybe we can cover
all of it if someone is uh say below the
poverty level. But those are some things
that we have to figure out and it's
going to take us time to adjust. But
this is why we wanted to hear about
these other aspects like uh you know
some of these things about helping the
support in the community. You know the
comment about having some of that
potential um support for a family or
community. It's not just about the
patient themselves. You know uh it's
really the whole community is the
patient and so that entire support
structure. So how might we be able to
help for that? Um, and so it's really
looking at those different things with
that caveat that if we were to try to
cover everything for everyone, $630,000
for a year is not going to go very far.
So, how do we do this the best way
possible? So, these are all great ideas
and we'll definitely have a lot more
conversations about them and trying to
figure it out. Katherine, I just saw
yours about the computers. That's a
great potential um you know concern and
potential issue because libraries are
really great as far as that or community
centers because they have computers but
they're not very private. So how many
people want to go and start talking
about you know their inner personal
thoughts and ideas and concerns while
sitting in a computer lab in a library
or you know things like that. So how
could we help with regard to that even a
little bit more? Maybe it's about
helping them figure out how to fund
private rooms or private locations or
things like that. And so we have to
figure there's a lot to determine and
how do we do this? And so these are
great ideas and they're going to help us
um and in this committee as we bring
them back because what we're going to
kind of do our next step is we're going
to take some of these ideas and uh and
Jorge and myself and some of the other
members of the team and work with Desba
in order to sort of say okay here are
some ideas. Here are some of the things
we're hearing. So, with that, I know we
only have a couple minutes left. Desba,
um, and I think we've heard some really
great comments. Are there other items we
need to cover or um, and by the way, if
people think of things outside of this,
you can send them to us. Um, they don't
necessarily just have to be part of
public comment, but I'm going to put the
information for the public comment in
the chat as well. I've got it on the
screen right now because you could still
send it to us even if you're past the
public comment for the meeting and we
will do our best to add it into the
different discussions. So,
>> um yes, thank you. So, we do have to
wrap it up um because we we uh we we
collectively have to get to the other
committee that is propagation later on
to hybrid if you're interested in that.
It's with Chris Piscus at three I
believe. Um, so you know, for me, I
always break down numbers and I'm just,
you know, I'm not saying that this is
the thing, but when we're looking at
$630,000
divided by the day for an entire year,
right? 365 days. And I hope next year is
not a leap year. It's a,00
it's it's it's it's not even 2,000 a
day, right? And I think Dominic, what
I'm what I'm also hearing too is like it
also depends
how many patients we're looking to be
able to uh take care of, let's just say
take care of in this medical trial for
the year. Um, and what are the costs
added up based on the uh, let's say,
let's just say fair market value of the
facilitators,
the cost of propagating, the cost of the
testing, and everything else adds up.
And I probably would assume that that's
more than $2,000
a day for all of that, right? So all of
that fair market value for the
facilitators, for the transportation,
for the medicine itself, and if we were
using Oregon and Colorado, New York
prices, we're talking a lot of money for
this one particular dose for this one
person.
And um I think that just to kind of
maybe think about it in those terms like
how are we going to maybe not
necessarily reach everyone because this
is a medicine that may be possible for
everyone if they're determined that it's
good and not everyone needs to take it
but for those who are qualifying for
those who are seeking it for those New
Mexicans who are willing to to to to
journey into this next part of their
life right um the amount of money that
we have is limited. It's a great amount
of money. Thank you very much everyone
for appropriating that money, but it is
very limited. And how are we going to be
able to best utilize it for the most um
I don't want to say neediest, but for
for those that are that are in going to
be moving forward with this next portion
of New Mexico's into the future, right?
Those people and the patient. How are we
going to collectively say these are the
people that we're going to work with.
this is how much we're going to allocate
and um what does it look like for the
cost. So with that in mind um you know
if you have any other broad ideas of
what it looks like it could be like you
know Dominic was saying like a sliding
scale are we looking and then also not
only that but elder care, child care,
etc. It it does add up and I'm thinking
like just this number in my head is
$10,000 for like one session fair market
value with whatever it is gas prices now
at five bucks. um you know it's going to
be it's it's it's a lot but we we can do
this. We can figure out how would be
best our the money that we can spend um
for and also to this just really quickly
um when we are able to help one person
with this medicine
one person.
Imagine the impact that that may have
for that person's family and for that
person's community.
And that value, that money value drops.
And I say that in the sense that like
we're getting that member of that
community back
online.
So with the limited amount of money we
have financially, it will make a huge
impact to that person's life. But we
also have to really think about the
financials with it.
So, um All right.
>> I think the only thing remaining is to
um uh determine the next meeting date.
>> Oh boy. Okay. Um next meeting date.
Let's see. Let's look in the calendar.
Um not Wednesdays, that's for sure. Um
there was a conflict today that I
avoided. Um
let's see. One, two. We can potentially
do the 23rd or the 24th. I'm not sure
what the calendar is for the other.
>> Um,
>> um, we could do we could schedule it for
1:00 on the 24th.
That time is open from the department
side.
>> Okay, let's do that. 24th on the
>> So, we'll set it up for 100 p.m. on
Tuesday the 24th of March.
>> Okay.
Okay.
>> All right. So, everyone put on their
thinking caps and uh reach out to more
people to join us and thank you very
much for your time today. Appreciate you
all. Thank you, Jorge and the
administration. You are a lovely
assistance. Appreciate so much.
>> Thank you, Desbomb. Thank you for
everybody for being here. And uh uh
we're if you're going in person to the
propagation meeting um we'll see you
over there in about an hour. um that's
scheduled to start at 3:00 and is over
at the Westside Community Center uh here
in Albuquerque. So otherwise, we'll see
everyone else on I'm sure on one of the
other meetings. Thank you everybody for
being here and helping.